Together today's regular reading of the 21-in, especially utility at 40, 40 days, day, and time,
out of two is in the nation by the director of all saints of history and church, Mary for help.
Let us pray.
Almighty God, our Heavenly Father, send down upon those who hold office in this city of Mayama, the spirit of wisdom, charity, and justice.
That was steadfast, purpose, they may faithfully serve in your offices to permit the well-being of all people.
Amen.
I pray to the leaders to the right of the United States of America to do it all the way for which it stands.
One nation, in the God, in this book, in the liberty and justice for all.
Mm-hmm.
I have a number of four, as public input, non-scheduled personal appearances, only on the audience that wishes to address the authority on any agenda.
I have been on item five as a consent agenda.
Staff is recommending item six through ten for the consent agenda.
Pull out item ten, just comment on it right away and so on.
Item six through none.
No.
For the consent agenda, I guess nine and ten are related on it.
Just reschedulating and approve the item.
So we'll pull out nine and ten.
So item six through eight.
Oh my God, motion later.
I'm going to take you to the right.
Second place.
Second.
Roll, roll.
Johnson.
Hi.
Western.
Good.
Hi.
Just a quick note on item nine.
We had had the surplus auction was originally scheduled for last Saturday and there was some confusion on some of the dates between the city and the county.
And so that auction is going to be rescheduled for July 9.
And that is item that we're dying.
So that we have a motion to approve the rescheduling.
Motion.
Second.
On second.
West.
Western.
Right.
Lewis.
Hi.
Johnson.
So.
Hi.
And item ten was approving the list of items to be sold auction.
I'll make a motion to approve that list.
Do we have a second?
I'll say.
Full call.
So.
I have Johnson.
Lewis.
I.
Western.
Item 11.
Security.
프로 monochrome.
That's the 30 basins three entrats process.
uuAPPLAUSE že0k.
This is the.
Uh, third bank that we've gotten online to take till repayment so that's kind of that's very nice.
I think it's the big convenient.
for our customers. If it pretty, they will begin taking payments on the 27th, which is next Monday.
Okay, same agreement. Same agreement. Same agreement to no change, is everything just the same.
Okay, great. I'll certainly be a convenience. And the other two is already started.
Yes, yes, and it's running well so far.
Okay, which is Welch and First Nation. Yes.
And so we're adding security bank to the Linux tab. We add security. We'll have seven locations up from
one location to be able to pay to these folks. Great. Yeah. And that includes all their drive through.
Yes. Great. So do we have most of the blue on 11?
Yes. And the second. Second.
Gold hole.
This. I. Justin. I.
Justin. All right. So. All right.
I didn't fall off. Resolution authorizing the sale issue. It's in delivery of certificates of
indebtedness of the authority to provide funds to refinance certain outstanding indebtedness of the authority,
authorizing sale there up in a discount, and waiting competitive bidding there on.
Mr. Nito. How are you?
I'm doing well, man. Are you doing? Mr. Chairman. I guess you're.
Thank you. It's a good opportunity to be here. I appreciate the opportunity to be here again and discuss this
a little bit more detail. At one of the budget sessions, we had a little discussion on that. That this would be
forthcoming. And since that time had some extensive discussions with the units for as the market is
concerned. And my, the guys I work with would accuse me of using this way too much, but it's kind of
come to strike while the iron's hot. And I have a big blister that I've got from my lawnmower
exhaust, so I strike while the iron's hot. It's sealed into my brain. So I'm back here to just discuss this
with you. Let me give you a little bit of history. I'm going to pass this out. This is similar to the
saying. The same information passed out last time. It's updated. We had a little bit of growth in sales tax,
but I'm going to go back a little bit to the history of what has brought us to this point. Back in
around 2010, we did a street bond issue that we voted a 0.65 sales tax it passed prior to that.
There had been an attempt to, I believe, at a one cent. We came on board and got a 0.65 past. We issued bonds
to be serviced by that 0.65 percent sales tax. A few years later, we came in and there was a project to be
done at the stadium for the college. And there was an extensive discussion on the possibilities.
And at that time, it was the general consensus that we did not want to have any additional sales
tax or any rate increases or anything. We didn't want to have any out-of-pocket expense to borrow
about $8.8 million. So we put together a plan that had long-range possibilities. We came back and we
amended the sales tax to service both the street bonds and this additional debt on the college.
We did what was called a ban, a bond anticipation note. There was five years. We didn't want any
current interest. So we have not been paying any interest on that issue. That was done in 13.
It matures in 15. I was here in five years, which is 18, but we can call it at the end of this year.
And by the way, stop if it gets confusing, because I had to rethink it, I had about three and a half hours to think this back through on the way up.
So I think I've got it all back down and Rudy, you help me because you're hearing hearing hearing all this.
I remember.
But anyway, so we did the bond anticipation though.
Well, we had the sales tax that was amended to take care of both of these issues. It goes on forever.
But it can only be used to satisfy these two bond requirements.
Now what we come to the conclusion, now what we've done is starting to take the next step on our plan, which is always planned.
And that is we're refinancing both the short term five-year bond anticipation though, and the remainder of the street bonds.
What that's going to require is using that same point 65% sales tax.
For an additional, we're going to grab with a 30-year bond issue that is going to be completely satisfied and taken care of by that existing sales tax.
Over 30 years, with no growth projected, and you can see on that sheet, we'll have about a $35-40,000 surplus every year.
Now, if we have any kind of growth that would just increase, and we can address all that being addressed, that overage, as he sees fit.
But we've done it from a conservative standpoint, no growth projected in sales tax.
You had 1,830,000, collected this last 12 months on that 0.65%.
It will take care of about a million, $91,92,000 debt service.
You'll have that left over.
Now, a couple of different things that have come into play, and really I think we talked about this.
We've had some discussions as far as how long the original intent of the extension was.
Well, one of the key factors is that when we did the stadium bonds, it was larger than we first planned, and we had not been paying an interest on it.
That has been capitalized. That's going to be taken care of in this bond issue.
What was the rate on that?
At the, it was 4.2 percent.
Yes, and I want to say this since you brought up right.
We've got these at about a 380.
There's some 3.8 percent fixed for 30 years.
If we were to price them today, we would...
You'll use it. Put this in real thin lead, because it could change tomorrow.
But if we were in the market today, we'd be under 3.5 percent.
There were some issues that priced today that were a little bit better credit than we are, because our larger community and everything else.
But they were substantially lower than that.
But if we were to go into the market today, we would be under 3.5 percent.
That could change tomorrow.
But with the way the feds have been meeting, we think we can...
We don't think much of doing change before the election.
So, but when it does change, you might want to hold on, because it may...
As we say, that interest rates are trickled down and chewed up.
But that kind of rings up to speed.
What this does is it nets you enough to take care of completely of what's called the escrow.
It wipes out the old bond issues.
Those were really no longer in existence.
We're no longer obligated on those.
They have...
of ESCO funds that take care of the principal and interest, we start paying just on these
two bond issues with that 0.65%.
Goes for 30 years, we can probably get about an eight-year call, means any time after
right years, we can pay them off early, without a penalty.
And that in a nutshell, I think kind of brings us up to where we are today.
What I was going to mention earlier, you know, we had, and really I think this is one thing
one of your concerns, as far as we did some forecasting early on, we didn't know it, we were
going to have to take the full 30 years.
We could actually, if you utilized all of this money, you could probably chop it's 28 years.
We're also doing it two years earlier than we anticipated, and we were going to, originally
plan on doing it in 2018, but we put that call in there specifically for this reason, the
things predecessor, one of the ability for you to be able to refund this early, that's why we can
do a call in three years and not have to wait a full five.
So that's what has taken this and lowered it, but we want to use the full 30 years from
a conservative standpoint.
Now I'm going through this in a fast and furious way, it's a complicated transaction, I'll
be glad to answer any questions that you might have, you have a time to leave it.
Jill, put out a time table.
Yes, sir.
The after question is I wouldn't appreciate you going over the time table.
Okay.
Thank you for a lot of our members, this is the first time they have done a bond issue and I'd like
to make sure they're comfortable with the process.
What questions so far on this?
I talked a lensing for just a few minutes before the meeting.
Right now we're paying 91,000 a month towards the current issue, although as Greg said, we've
capitalized the interest to it.
We're paying on the original Street Law 91,000 a month.
If you take this number and the middle of column series, it's about the same amount, so our
payments would basically continue as they have been.
And Greg's right, the original amount we were talking about on this stadium, I don't remember exactly
what it was, but it was seven and a half or so, it ended up being 8.8 and then we capitalized
a million, one, and interest, so really, the stadium portion of it today is about right
at 10,000,000,000,000,000,000,000 when you can't be interested.
The original bond issue was 12,450, I think, is what we ended up our total cost, so, to me,
that kind of explains why it's going out to 30, and first, I guess, you were here last time,
I didn't understand how it had shrugged out six or seven years, but certainly the math makes
sense to me on that part of it, and certainly I think taking advantage of the low interest
rate is the right thing to do, I don't think we can wait two years, we have the luxury of
doing that, but I think that we've got a lot of exposure coming after the election, and
then probably don't want to take that risk, I don't know that it would be prudent, and I think
would Greg is pointing out.
than what I've seen too, is we're at really historic lows.
So I can't imagine getting that much lower,
but I can certainly imagine getting higher.
Needs, so we follow the Treasury market,
what you kind of, it's where the municipal market
fluctuates on.
And we've been watching it hit 50 year lows right now.
I mean, it's pretty amazing,
but we really didn't have a sense of where new issues were
until just the last few days in everybody's just going,
okay, it's time.
I mean, there's, you know, 50 to 75 basis wins,
which is half to three quarters of a percent
under what everybody kind of thought the market was,
even conservatively and so that's why it's just like, okay.
Because the other side of it is, if you do it now,
could the market go lower, it's possible,
but if it goes up, then you lose the ability
to take care of this issue with the 0.65 since sales tax.
That's what I think is a key factor.
Right now is the time that you can take care of it,
and still have that little bit of a cushion.
And, you know, because I did a quick and dirty on the way up,
every quarter of a percent, if it goes up one quarter of a percent,
that's $30,000 a year over the life of the issue on average.
So that would eat up that surplus.
Obviously, if it goes up a half, then you're out of the money from the sales.
And I'm not, again, it's an easy sell from my standpoint
as a financial advisor, because that's right there in the numbers.
So if it goes up a half point, that current point 65,
based on our current sales tax generation level,
won't be enough to satisfy the debt,
and I have to start pulling money from what is typically
goes into the general budget to help carry that debt.
And then the situation is not, it's not, it's not $250.
Now, I can go, I don't have a copy of that.
Do you have a copy?
Here you go.
Not for burden provided, I didn't worth it.
This is just a time table, it's tentative.
By the way, there are any other questions so far.
And I just got a great answer.
And again, you jump in, maybe even David is point out.
Because the voters approved this,
when we, what we call the stadium election,
there's not a vote required to do any of the assets
for taxpayers, it's just something that the council can authorize.
That is correct, Mr.
Yes, or that was contemplated and discussed and reflected
in the ballot question, at least in such terms
that there's no prohibition on the council
or in the C.A. taking the sanction.
OK, time table?
Yes, please.
This obviously today is 21st.
We can discuss and propose a refunding on the 28th.
You can pass the resolutions.
I'll address that in just a minute.
July 1st, senior information is
the rating A to C standard for, 15th receive the rating A to Cs.
And we're going to look at insurance, which
is a, it's a shirty bond.
For years, they were not really effective.
Because it rolled down with a,
There's only one and we're all, they used to be five or six, it had AAA ratings and you could buy insurance and that gave your bond issue a AAA rating and you traded better.
This now is just strictly a function of the numbers.
We do that.
We look at what a premium might be and we've all set it against the savings in interest.
And if it works, we do it.
If it doesn't, we don't.
So, and then the span, they're usually the rating agencies are a little bit quicker.
But we think that everybody's probably meeting about like we are and trying to get into the market.
We'll receive the close by the 29th.
The August 1st will distribute the preliminary official statement, which is the sales document.
That's basically it's put together.
We put it together in conjunction with the underwriter.
It's distributed to potential buyers.
And then we have a pre-sale and then a sale date.
August 10th, we sell bonds and then September 1st, we close the bond issue.
Now I want to just real quickly address a couple of things.
We may, if you so desire, let me say this first.
The way your agenda is structured, you can actually vote on these resolutions tonight and proceed.
If you don't, totally understand that.
If you've never been through this, it can be a challenge.
You can do it and we can start the process and that would accelerate this a little bit.
These are conservative issues, conservative time tables.
We really want to do the pricing and selling earlier than what is on your table.
But we're shooting for a September 1 closing.
I won't get into all the mechanics because your actual call date is December 1.
That's within 90 days.
It affects where you can do advanced refundings in the future.
I don't want to muddy the waters.
Just trust me on that.
But what we do is it's called a delayed settlement.
We try to get in the market, secure the rate and then not close until September 1st.
But that time table is tentative.
Again, if you wanted to move tonight, you can, if you want to wait until the 28th, that's fine.
You can.
When does the Fed made it again?
Is it, they don't meet for, is it September?
But they've made it again?
They've been doing some strange meetings.
I mean that would be that concern we would have is if they met in between and there was an increase in rates.
But I don't, I don't know when they made it again.
I can find that.
I mean, I'll try to not to be right now.
But that's just, that's a tentative time table.
There really, I think that what happened this time is there is anticipation that the Fed was going to raise rates in the last several weeks.
We had that horrible jobs report.
The market had already built in a little bit of an increase and then all of a sudden boom rate shot down.
And that's what we're on right now.
It's actually bounced about the last week, but it's still, it's an amazing rate.
And frankly, since we're going to have another voting meeting next week potentially, I'm going to ask you about it during my comments.
What a week problem is that we have a much different set of order to be considered at the...
a lot of you have never dealt with these things before and even after the
back you might think. Here's a question that I came up with, gives you an
opportunity to do that. I just didn't want to just hand this to you and
say please vote on it. Although everything are same, we're in very good shape. One
thing that I think Greg mentioned is S&P, Standard & Poor's. If you've ever
dealt with Standard & Poor's they basically look at the financial health
of the city and not just the city government they look at the overall
community. So it's a rating of Miami that you will get. Some people look at
and say do I want to invest in Miami? So that is a very important step that we're
going to be taking to make sure that they know that our sales taxes are stable or
employment basis are stable, that this is a dedicated sales tax that pays it back.
I mean that rating is going to be very critical. One thing that we've done since the
last time we were rated at least ready for bond is we've moved our retirement plan. I wonder if
that will have it in the positive effect on the plan has been positive.
It's out to just really it will. Because we are dealing with that on a regular basis
the unfunded retirement plans that are being addressed not just here but it's a
nationwide issue. So we are bad the money we have and reserve are critical. That's one
of the things they look at. And then also just employment I mean think about 30
years ago what our bond rating would have been after a good richest gone but our
employment by now is stable. So it's very important that they look at things like that as
well. And again and Dean you're exactly right if they can contact you contact me in
between this week and next week any questions that might pop up across the board.
You know if you if you again not an official vote if you think it's something you
all want to do. I mentioned this to Dean also if it's kind of a consensus not an
official vote but if everybody says you know if nothing jumps up and bites us I'd like
to do this and we'll go ahead and actually start putting our stuff together as far as packets
and everything else. But that's that's entirely up to you. If you want to take no action it's
completely. I think you should go ahead and put your package together because we want to
be positioned at least to take advantage of the right. Any you know it's no obligation until we
actually get everything done so. Any other questions for Greg? There's lots and lots
of information you can provide. Lots. You have any predictions on the election how that's
going to affect me. Yes I do. If we do it 20% correction and how to say it's a little
reflect on the bonds just hypothetically. That's tough. I always I'm like the guy on
the radio that's a stock market expert. He says do you think the market's going to
whip it down? He says yes but not right away. That's my prediction. Now we I've been doing this
for 35 years. And this
There's a whole lot of head scratching going on in the mud.
The mud is just on top of the cross.
It is.
The reactions, the things you know, there used to be the inverse relationships between certain aspects
of the markets, whether it's gold and silver and stocks and trash, doesn't exist anymore.
I mean, and so I'm not trying to, I really am trying to duck your question, but not, but it's
a municipal bonds are still the most secure places to borrow money.
They really aren't born.
They, they really aren't.
They're living state, then we're municipal bonds to get right to it.
So that's, that's why the rates are so low is that they're so little risk.
It's the flight, what's called the flight to quality.
He's got a great.
It's quality rated municipal bonds are still building in everybody's eyes.
So, colloquium idea of pricing the insurance to see if you can buy down the money.
If you get a number game, it is, yes, it makes sense or it doesn't, but it is.
That's the idea of looking at it.
Hey, other questions for Greg?
Any comments?
I think we've made our comments as time to move and just want to make sure you're comfortable
when we do it.
But if we're going to have to do this in our later this time, I'll be the best time we can do it.
Okay.
Thank you, Greg.
Thank you.
I don't throw a team.
Another new business.
Any new business team?
Not on this agenda.
Four teams staff are fortunate in their packet.
They're any questions for staff if not we'll move on to the committee announcements.
Any announcements?
16.
There's motion to adjourn.
We have motion to adjourn.
That motion to adjourn.
And second.
Second.
Hold on.
That's in.
All right.
I'm here.
You need to do all the event.
I'm trying to get used to it.
This is also an item on the regular council.
You're leading.
I think it's for the same thing.